<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Josh Peterson</title>
    <description>Media Art</description>
    <link>https://josh-peterson.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://josh-peterson.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2016 11:32:46 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2016 11:32:46 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Electronic Earthwork</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;How might we make interactive land art? This project is one answer for this question, and I want to open-source the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to see people making art with technology continue to become more I had been considering sharing everything, and then American Public Art in Boston created a patreon where they’re starting to release info around hardware / software / materials / process and it inspired me to take this leap. This work will take a number of months to execute and I’ll be sharing updates at major milestones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was in college in Seattle I made an interactive project using a big handheld spotlight, a pair of walkie-talkies, and an arduino. Seattle is very hilly, and on one hill I put the spotlight. Then from another hill one mile away, you could control the spotlight with your voice. At that distance, the light looked like any other streetlight – a tiny spec. But it only turned on when you were speaking into the walkie-talkie. I made a short film about setting the project up and using it, the light flashing on and off with every syllable you spoke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make another version of this project in Seattle again, but at a very large scale. Seattle is surrounded by mountains – to the east are the Cascades, and to the west are the Olympics. They’re a defining feature of the landscape – they’re the horizon, the walls of the container that holds the city (though the mountains themselves are icons of the wilderness that surrounds the city). I want to put a light out in these mountains, 35 miles away, that anyone can control in the city by visiting a url on their phone and speaking into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some thoughts about what the piece means to me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	It may turn out to be an extreme digital interaction that will be worthwhile in itself. Someone using this will never have experienced anything like it before. Seeing a light turn on when you speak at the distance of 1 mile, or even 100 yards, is uncanny. At 35 miles it may be really strange and awe-inspiring.
•	In one sense, this is conceptually similar with posting something on the internet. You hit a button on your phone with your fingers, and thousands of miles away a server activates, and pixels on someone else’s phone sends light into their eyeballs. I’m interested in playing with bringing this action-at-a-distance to the largest scale that one person can immediately experience.
•	What is a city? What are the limits of a city? All these lights and other utilities that surround us and are interactive to varying degrees, what do they say to us? Are they benevolent?
•	I take a lot of inspiration from the Light and Space movement, especially Robert Irwin.
o	The idea of site-specific art: a piece that leverages the features of its environment. It can only exist in that place it was designed for – if you move it, it’s changed. The context is part of the work.
o	The tactic of stripping a work down further and further because that’s one way to make art that can get at fundamental principles of experience. This piece is really just one pixel, far away.
o	A fascination with the perception of space. I’m interested in how drawing attention to this tiny light as far as the eye can see will protract or flatten someone’s sense of distance and their larger environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now onto the how. There are a few different components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[image]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A light visible at 35 miles needs to be extremely bright, so only a radio tower beacon will do. This will be powered by a solar generator consisting of a solar panel, a battery, and a BMS (Battery Management System) that handles the charging and output. There are newer LED beacons that use less power. Radio tower obstruction lights are normally omnidirectional (the unidirectional ones are typically strobes, which won’t work for this), but I actually want focused light. Additionally, the light may not be bright enough to be very visible at 35 miles. So I may build a custom reflector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The light will be turned on and off using a solid state relay controlled by a cellular-radio enabled IOT board. I’ve selected the Particle Electron because it’s more plug and play than using other things e.g. the Raspberry Pi for this application. Resilient, if it power dies temporarily it’ll come on and connect to the internet automatically. This would take work to configure with a R-pi. Also probably lower power. It has a community and core libraries for TCP client. I’ll get a cell antenna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cell data. Woah boy, it’s weird. Particle as a data service, but I’ll be using too much at the rate I’m sending (include calc from forum). CDMA vs GSM. Verizon doesn’t work with particle because GSM only. Rates are weird, expensive. Going with Ting, which is a good deal, pay as you go data somewhat? More made for iot, too.
But cellular still wtf because of latency, estimating signal (opensignal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web infra:
Socket io because ease of use, perf not important for # of users (100 max?)
Basic check for location using cdn, then maybe gps although it adds friction. OSM.
Logic: mixes all incoming signals, dynamic based on # inputs.
Dashboard: logging for prototyping, documentation, managing bad actors
Passes to iot board via tcp&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Front end: 
Don’t send audio – privacy. Low pass filter essentially, sending numbers over websocket.
Fps?
For my project, I just need:
•	One device over cellular
•	Receive a number 0 - 255 and pwm an output pin accordinly
•	Rate: Ideally 25 times per second, maybe 10/sec minimum
•	16 hours a day
Running the math…
This page1 says a short particle.publish is 128 bytes. So 128 bytes x 25/sec x 60 sec x 60 min x 16 hours = 184 megabytes. Just per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Custom reflector – may not be bright enough. Design + fab parabolic reflector and/or Fresnel lens. Brightness overall might mean more dynamic range, better also for foggy condition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some non-technical challenges to executing this piece too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selecting a site. Since I don’t live in Seattle, I’ve used google maps to stake out a lot of the land surrounding the city. I also need permission. To the east, the land covering the nearby Cascades is managed by a corporation. To the west, it’s managed by the National Forest Service. Using NFS land is highly regulated and there’s a protracted process, and it would be much easier to just send the corporation a letter. NFS actually requires that you pursue non-public options for your use first, so I’ll go with that. I might create a video, or pursue an even more creative tact. Christos art required a lot of this, and the process of getting permission even became part of the work. It’s a different story when you are an early career unknown artist, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, I may be required to get a Professional Engineer to look over my light and wiring and make sure it’s not a fire hazard. Even if it’s not legally required, I might do it anyway because it will make me and probably my hosts feel better. PE’s are often engaged for public art projects. I need to find one though, and I’m not sure the best way to go about that. Been following some word of mouth leads with other artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I need to check that this light will be legal by FAA standards. It’s hard to understand if it is just by reading their regulations, because my use-case is so atypical – flashing white medium intensity at night. Usually it’s flashing red at night, or flashing white high intensity during the day. This may be allowed by I may have to make accommodations, for example I may have to put on the top of a ridge instead of on the side, or even put it on a radio tower, or even change the color to red.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setup is going to require flying over to Seattle, probably doing some fab there, and then assembling a team of people to help install. I’ll have to rent a truck and maybe get permits to access land. I may have to secure some space to do staging/testing. Then, I’ll also want to take footage of setting the project up to use in documentation/ video version of the work, and take footage of people using it while I’m there. So I’ll need to rent video equipment and do some storyboarding to plan what my final project ideal would be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publicity. I’m inspired by the Now Rise project and the confusion it caused. I also would like it to slowly catch on. That’s actually a key part of the work for me – the social dimension. I may flyer in places that have line of sight to break out of my social bubble without using press that I myself commission. Flyers will have to be designed carefully because of the type of messaging/framing they give the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front end design will have to be carefully considered too. It’ll be really minimal and dark so it doesn’t ruin people’s night vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there’s another problem that’s a crossover between tech and non-tech. Mitigating abuse. There might be bad actors, it’ll be possible to troll the game and make it unusable for other people. I’ll need to set up some quick and dirty defenses against people gaming it, as well as using it from other locations outside of Seattle, but I don’t think I’ll ever be able to totally protect it. Also what I have in mind will be really time intensive – like might take just as much time as writing the rest of the app, so I may have to work on it once the thing is already launched, hoping it won’t go viral and attract “hackers” right away.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://josh-peterson.com/blog/beacon-3/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://josh-peterson.com/blog/beacon-3/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Work-in-Progress</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a few blog posts on their way. Stay tuned for write-ups about projects in progress.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://josh-peterson.com/blog/welcome/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://josh-peterson.com/blog/welcome/</guid>
        
        
        <category>News</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
