<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Josh Peterson</title>
    <description>Media Art</description>
    <link>https://josh-peterson.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://josh-peterson.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2016 18:16:31 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2016 18:16:31 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>consumemusic.online</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;normal-size&quot;&gt;I’m working on a site. The URL is http://consumemusic.online. When you go to it, you’ll read something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Turn up your speakers. You are now listening to a sound that will never be heard again.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On June 20, 2015, a user named midi_man posted a link on reddit to the largest midi collection in existence. They had crawled hundreds of midi sites, and assembled virtually all of the files publicly available into one archive. 130,000 files / 3.65Gb of pure midi. This archive represents the cumulative musical achievement of humankind, as well as several animal species.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This site plays the archive from front to back. As each visitor plays part of a song, that portion is consumed and will never be played again by anyone else.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your browser started playing where someone else left off. But you don’t have to stay here - you can scroll and listen to whatever remains. You can even takeover another listener’s song and kick them off their spot. Everything you hear will be heard once, and only once. Together, we can all burn this one down.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I made up some prototypes in Sketch:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/consume-music-prototypes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Prototypes&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the songs are in the archive laid out end to end, left to right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can scroll horizontally. To the left is the boneyard of all the songs that have been played. To the right are unplayed songs, mostly. The song you’re playing has a red leading edge at the current time. You can click on any unplayed song to start playing it instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see when someone else is currently playing a song because the edge is yellow. If you click on their song, they’ll get booted to the next available blue space. You’ll pick up where they left off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The piece is meant to be compared / contrast with how we collectively create and consume media in communities online. It’s an opportunity for the swarm behavior of thousands of people on the internet, usually only imagined or experienced incidentally, to be brought into focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s something further, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 400px; margin: 0 auto&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/mario.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Mario Text Gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But - with the digital, what is also summoned at will are rules and relationships. What if, by setting some rules, we make a digital artifact consumable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was here, but then you put it in your body, and now it’s gone. At some point along the way it was transformed into something else. The object is no longer here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or…it’s still here, but it has a different state? Or at least the idea of it is still here, but with a different state attached. Maybe the experience of it is the only thing that is ever consumed. Even with an eternal music object, the experience was always consumed.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-site-is-about-how-we-bracket-infinity&quot;&gt;This site is about how we bracket infinity.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music, as a cultural entity, seems infinite. All the music in all the earth – now and since forever – who can count it all? But it’s actually not infinite. Music requires people, to create it and to experience it, and there is a finite number of people that have ever lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, what if we assembled all of the music into a whole, as much as we could at least?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if we took all of the pieces, that were before so disparate, and by creating relationships between them, formed a mass out of them, that we could treat as one? That you could actually be presented with, that you actually had the means to explore if you had enough time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assembling all the midi on the internet is not the same as assembling all the music in the world. The internet doesn’t contain all the music, just like it doesn’t contain all the knowledge, much less all the experience. But the internet was and is the primary vehicle for cheesy midi adaptations of songs, and so this archive is maybe a solid attempt at building a corpus that represents an entirety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or maybe it just directs the mind’s eye toward the gap between the real infinity, and our best attempt. But who knows how big that gap is? Because your idea of the real infinite is just an abstraction anyway. Well, this app is just an abstraction too.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-site-is-about-when-we-say-two-things-are-different-and-when-we-say-theyre-the-same&quot;&gt;This site is about when we say two things are different, and when we say they’re the same.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music is not infinite. So in your mind, assemble the totality of ALL of music. What’s the difference between that and infinity? Between the all-of-it and the infinite?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about all of music is tough because music isn’t just the artifacts. It’s also the lived experience of the thing. We typically have one of a couple different situations. 1) Listening to a concert, a live performance that may only exist in that moment, shared together amongst a dozen, a hundred, a hundred thousand people. 2) Listening to recorded music, a static digital artifact of a performance, alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;consumemusic.online is an inversion of this. Thousands of people together will experience a one-time performance of a digital artifact, a concert that’s thousands of hours long. But formally something weird is happening, because each person will only experience a small piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a parallel to our experience of social media. How often have you heard of someone complaining of some phenomenon “on Facebook” which you yourself have not witnessed? And yet we all refer to “Facebook” as if it’s one entity, where it’s really maybe closer to our own little room. Totally unique, totally dynamic, different from everyone else’s and different from one moment to the next. Maybe we don’t appreciate this fact. But if you pull up consumemusic.online and you’re the single solitary person that heard “Hey Jude,” maybe you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you think about the totality of music from day to day, this is what is happening all along. All of these individual experiences are happening distributed throughout millions of different places, but together they sum up to the sublime reality of what music actually is. No one person gets to experience that though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When two people each view a work of art, and that work of art showed them each something different, how different does the thing have to be for us to no longer say they saw the same art? If a work’s identity isn’t in the details, what is it in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone who goes to the site will experience this piece of net art. But will everyone experience it the same? Maybe to prove they won’t, we’ll show each of them something different. Maybe we’ll play them each a different song. And when they come back again, we’ll do the same. Something different.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://josh-peterson.com/blog/consume-music-online-progress-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://josh-peterson.com/blog/consume-music-online-progress-1/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Work-in-Progress</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Electronic Earthwork</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;How might we make interactive land art? This project is one answer for this question, and I am open-sourcing it. This work will take a number of months to execute and I’ll be sharing updates at major milestones, with in-progress information about hardware, software, materials, process, and theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was in college in Seattle I made an interactive project using a big handheld spotlight, a pair of walkie-talkies, and an arduino. Seattle is very hilly, and on one hill I put the spotlight. Then from another hill one mile away, you could control the spotlight with your voice. At that distance, the light looked like any other streetlight – a tiny spec. But it only turned on when you were speaking into the walkie-talkie. I made a short film about setting the project up and using it, the light flashing on and off with every syllable you spoke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make another version of this project in Seattle again, but at a very large scale. Seattle is surrounded by mountains – to the east are the Cascades, and to the west are the Olympics. They’re a defining feature of the landscape – they’re the horizon, the walls of the wilderness that contains the city. I want to put a light out in these mountains, 35 miles away, that anyone can control in the city by visiting a url on their phone and speaking into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/24302805?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Some thoughts about what the piece means to me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It may turn out to be an extreme digital interaction that will be worthwhile in itself. Someone using this will probably never have experienced anything like it before. Seeing a light turn on when you speak at the distance of 1 mile, or even 100 yards, is uncanny. At 35 miles it may be really strange and awe-inspiring.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In one sense, activating the light is conceptually similar with posting something on the internet. You hit a button on your phone with your fingers, and thousands of miles away a server does some unknown task, and then pixels on someone else’s phone sends light into their eyeballs. I’m interested in playing with bringing this action-at-a-distance to the largest scale that one person can immediately experience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is a city? What are the limits of a city? All these lights and other utilities that surround us and are interactive to varying degrees, what do they say to us? Are they benevolent?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I take a lot of inspiration from the Light and Space movement, especially Robert Irwin.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The idea of site-specific art: a piece that leverages the features of its environment. It can only exist in that place it was designed for – if you move it, it’s changed. The context is part of the work.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The tactic of stripping a work down further and further because that’s one way to make art that can get at fundamental principles of experience. This piece is really just one pixel, far away.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A fascination with the perception of space. I’m interested in how drawing attention to this tiny light as far as the eye can see will protract or flatten someone’s sense of distance and their larger environment.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-tech&quot;&gt;The Tech&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/beacon-redux-diagram.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Project Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is an audit over all the bases I have to cover to execute this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-light&quot;&gt;1. The Light&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A light visible at 35 miles needs to be extremely bright, so only a radio tower beacon will do. This will be powered by a solar generator consisting of a solar panel, a battery, and a BMS (Battery Management System) that handles the charging and output. There are newer LED beacons that use less power. Radio tower obstruction lights are normally omnidirectional (the unidirectional ones are typically strobes, which won’t work for this), but I actually want focused light. Additionally, the light may not still be bright enough to be as visible as I want at 35 miles. I may need a parabolic reflector and/or a fresnel lens, and it may have to be custom designed and fabricated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-brains&quot;&gt;2. The Brains&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The light will be turned on and off using a solid state relay controlled by a cellular-radio enabled IOT board. I’ve selected the &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.particle.io/collections/electron&quot;&gt;Particle Electron&lt;/a&gt; because it’s more plug and play than using other things e.g. the Raspberry Pi for this application. It’ll provide some resiliency, for example if it crashes or if the power dies temporarily, afterwards it’ll come on and connect to the internet and the server again automatically. This would take work to configure with a R-pi. It’s also probably lower power. It has a pretty active community and core libraries for a TCP client, which I will use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-signal&quot;&gt;3. The Signal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cell data. Woah boy, it’s weird. There are a lot of things we take for granted when we’re on wifi that we can’t with cellular data. You can see the cracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particle actually offers cellular data as a service with an API, but I’ll be using too much data at the rate I’m sending to be able to take advantage of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some napkin math about how much data I’ll need:
I’ll need send a number describing the loudness of someone’s voice from the client to the server at around 25 times per second to achieve a time-resolution similar to video. Maybe as little as 10 times per second will be acceptable, but I won’t know until I prototype. I think my transmission unit might be around 128 bytes, but not sure on that either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;128 bytes x 25/sec x 60 sec x 60 min x 16 hours max = 184 megabytes per day, maybe 5-6 gb per month maximum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two major cellular radio systems: CDMA and GSM. The Particle Electron only works with GSM providers. I’m in the USA, Verizon and Sprint are out because they’re CDMA, and AT&amp;amp;T and T-Mobile are the major GSM options. Rates for IoT device tiers from these carriers can be hard to understand and not that great of a deal I’ve found. At this point I’m going with a different carrier called &lt;a href=&quot;https://ting.com/&quot;&gt;Ting&lt;/a&gt;, which is made for IoT, and is a little more pay-as-you-go which is especially great for development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of other hurdles with cellular: latency and estimating signal strength. Latency will be explored in a hardware prototype soon. For signal strength, there’s a handy tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensignal.com/&quot;&gt;OpenSignal&lt;/a&gt; that crowd sources signal strength readings across the map, and the cell providers have maps of their own you can download too. I’ll get a big cell antenna to boost the signal, as a just-in-case measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-front-end&quot;&gt;4. The Front End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone in the Seattle are should be able to go to a url on a smartphone and begin controlling the light with their voice. The best way to send this type of streaming data is with websockets. I won’t send audio itself, because it’s bad for privacy and I don’t really need that high of resolution anyway. I’ll be essentially doing a lowpass filter in the browser, and sending a number representing the volume at a rate of 10 to 25 times per second, most likely. I’d like to keep the interface very minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-back-end&quot;&gt;5. The Back End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is going to be a real-time app that revolves around streaming data from many clients simultaneously. There are several websocket libraries that have better performance than socket.io, but actually for the number of users that will be using the app at once (maybe 100 max?) performance is not that important, and socket.io seems like the best choice for ease of development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will need to be some logic for mixing all incoming signals. I’ll write more on this later, but for now think of it as summing all incoming signals up to a certain limit, with some additional dynamic behavior when there are more than 5-10 simultaneous users. Then, the backend will pass the final output down to the Particle board via TCP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least in the beginning I’ll need to set up a system for logging and a dashboard to see the data and perform some administration actions. There are 3 reasons for this: for prototyping and iterative design in early stages; for documentation of how people used it after the project is over; and maybe even for managing bad actors while the piece is in play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;land-use-logistics-design&quot;&gt;Land Use, Logistics, Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are some non-technical challenges to executing this piece too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selecting a site. Since I don’t live in Seattle anymore, I’ve used google maps to stake out a lot of the land surrounding the city. When I was visiting in October, I went on a hike in one potential location, and confirmed that it’s possible to see radio tower lights from more than 35 miles away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also need permission. To the east, the land covering the nearby Cascades is managed by a corporation. To the west, it’s managed by the National Forest Service. Using NFS land is highly regulated and there’s a protracted process to gain access, so it would be much easier to just send the corporation a letter. Anyway, NFS actually requires that you pursue non-public options for your use first. To ask for permission, I might think about some creative options like a video pitch or even something more out there. The work of &lt;a href=&quot;http://christojeanneclaude.net/&quot;&gt;Christo and Jeanne-Claude&lt;/a&gt; art required a lot of securing agreements with public agencies and private property owners, and the process of getting permission even became part of the work. It’s a different story when you are an early career unknown artist, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, I may be required to get a Professional Engineer to look over my light’s specs and make sure it’s not a fire hazard. Even if it’s not legally required, I might do it anyway because it will make me and probably my hosts feel better. PE’s are often engaged for public art projects. I need to find one though, and I’m not sure the best way to go about that. Been following some word of mouth leads with other artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I need to check that this light will be legal by FAA standards. It’s hard to understand if it is just by reading their regulations, because my use-case is so atypical – flashing white medium intensity at night. Usually it’s flashing red at night, or flashing white high intensity during the day. This may be allowed by I may have to make accommodations, for example I may have to put on the top of a ridge instead of on the side, or even put it on a radio tower, or even change the color to red.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setup is going to require flying from NYC to Seattle, probably doing some fabrication there, and then getting a team of people to help install. I may have to secure some space to do staging/testing. I’ll have to rent a truck and maybe get permits to access land. Then, I’ll also want to take footage of setting the project up to use in documentation/ video version of the work, and take footage of people using it while I’m there. So I’ll need to rent video equipment and do some storyboarding to plan what my final project ideal would be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publicity. The social dimension of this piece is really important to me. I’m inspired by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.allriseseattle.org/robertmontgomery/&quot;&gt;All Rise&lt;/a&gt; project and the confusion it caused. People didn’t really know what to make of it at first, and there was some question about who was behind it, what their motives are, or even was it art. I would like this piece to slowly catch on in the same way. I may flyer in places that have line of sight to break out of my social bubble without using press. Flyers will have to be designed carefully because of the type of messaging/framing they give the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front end design will have to be carefully considered too. It’ll be really minimal, and dark so it doesn’t ruin people’s night vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there’s another problem that’s a crossover between tech and non-tech. Mitigating abuse. There might be bad actors, it’ll be possible to troll the game and make it unusable for other people. I’ll need to set up some quick and dirty defenses against people gaming it, as well as using it from other locations outside of Seattle, but I don’t think I’ll ever be able to totally protect it. Also what I have in mind will be really time intensive – like might take just as much time as writing the rest of the app, so I may have to work on it once the thing is already launched, hoping it won’t go viral and attract “hackers” right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, that was a long summary. In upcoming posts I’ll examine some of the individual components more in-depth!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://josh-peterson.com/blog/light-progress-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://josh-peterson.com/blog/light-progress-1/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Work-in-Progress</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about the ways media artists can share technical knowledge, process, and theory with each other. If this was done more, it’s possible it’ll lead to more critical art and more meaningful experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I saw that New American Public Art, a studio out of Boston that makes interactive pieces, created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patreon.com/NAPA/posts&quot;&gt;Patreon&lt;/a&gt; where they’re open sourcing a lot of information from their work. I’ve decided to take the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be using this space to share write-ups about projects in progress, as well as criticism of other work I see around me. ✌️&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://josh-peterson.com/blog/welcome/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://josh-peterson.com/blog/welcome/</guid>
        
        
        <category>News</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
